Guide to the William Anthony Papers,1955-2013 (Bulk 1976-2013) MSS.081
Fales Library and Special Collections
William Anthony Papers
1955-2022
1976-2013
Fales Library and Special Collections
Anthony, William
MSS.081
2 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons and 1 folder in shared housing
William Anthony (1934-2022) was an American painter, illustrator, and graphic artist working in satire. This William Anthony Papers primarily contain facsimiles of Anthony's work, documenting his artistic career from 1976 though 2004. There are also some original artworks, photographs of Anthony, and other personal materials.
Biographical Note
William Anthony (1934-2022) was an American painter, illustrator, and graphic artist working in satire. Anthony was born in Ft. Monmouth, New Jersey in 1934, and grew up in Washington State. He graduated from Yale in 1958, majoring in history and taking art courses, including Josef Albers's drawing course. Shortly after graduation he moved to the San Francisco Bay Area where he studied briefly at art schools.
Anthony taught figure drawing at a commercial art school in San Francisco in 1962. This experience resulted in a his first book, A New Approach to Figure Drawing, 1965, (Crown, NY, and Odhams, 1967, London). His other books, all of satirical drawings, include Bible Stories, 1978, (The Jargon Society, Winston-Salem), Bill Anthony's Greatest Hits, (1988, The Jargon Society), and War Is Swell, 2000, (Smart Art Press, Santa Monica).
His drawings have been commissioned for Artforum, The Paris Review, Art In America, and by Andy Warhol for his magazine Interview.
The Museum of Modern Art, the Metropolitan Museum of Art, the Whitney Museum, the Guggenheim Museum, the Brooklyn Museum and 20 other museums include Anthony's work in their collections.
Anthony lived in New York since 1964 and passed away in 2022.
Scope and Contents
This collection primarily contains facsimiles of Anthony's work, documenting his artistic career from 1976 though 2022. There are also some original artworks, photographs of Anthony, and other personal materials.
Arrangement
This collection was arranged and described by the donor. Minor changes have been made by the archivist to improve accessibility.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The William Anthony Papers were donated to NYU's Fales Library and Special Collections by William Anthony in 1996, 2009 and 2013. In 2022, an accretion was donated by the estate of William Anthony; the accession number associated with this accretion is 2023.009.
Drawings; Mail Art.; Artists -- United States.; Photographs.; Announcements.; Anthony, William
- Series I: Record of artwork, 1976-2005
  - Artwork (copies), 1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Artwork (copies), 1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Artwork (copies), 1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Artwork (copies), 1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Artwork (copies), 1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Artwork (copies), 1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Artwork (copies), 1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Artwork (copies), 1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Artwork (copies), 1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Artwork (copies), 1983 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Artwork (copies), 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Artwork (copies), 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Artwork (copies), 1984 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Artwork (copies), 1985 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Artwork (copies), 1986 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Artwork (copies), 1987 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Artwork (copies), 1987 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Artwork (copies), 1987 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Artwork (copies), 1988 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Artwork (copies), 1989 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Artwork (copies), 1989 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Artwork (copies), 1990 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Artwork (copies), 1990 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Artwork (copies), 1991 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Artwork (copies), 1991 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Artwork (copies), 1992 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Artwork (copies), 1993 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Artwork (copies), 1993 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Artwork (copies), 1994 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Artwork (copies), 1994 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Artwork (copies), 1994 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Artwork (copies), 1995 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Artwork (copies), 1995 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Artwork (copies), 1996 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Artwork (copies), 1996 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Artwork (copies), 1997 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Artwork (copies), 1997 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Artwork (copies), 1997 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Artwork (copies), 1998 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Artwork (copies), 1998 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Artwork (copies), 1999 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Artwork (copies), 1999 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Artwork (copies), 1999 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Artwork (copies), 2000 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Artwork (copies), 2000 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Artwork (copies), 2000 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Artwork (copies), 2000 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Artwork (copies), 2001 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Artwork (copies), 2001 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Artwork (copies), 2002 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Artwork (copies), 2002 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Artwork (copies), 2003 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Artwork (copies), 2003 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Artwork (copies), 2003 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Artwork (copies), 2004 (Box 1, Folder 55)
- Series II: Original Artwork
  - "On the Beach", "High Sign", "Gunslinger", "Backside", "Signature", 1972-1994 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - "Sunny Side of the Street", "Three Strikes and You're Out", "High Roller", "Orangerie IV", 1982-1994 (Box 1, Folder 57)
- Series III: Personal material
  - Announcements of exhibits, review, etc..., 1991, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Personal photographs of William Anthony, Undated (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Photos and Xeroxes of artwork, 1960's (Box 1, Folder 60)
- Series IV: Miscellany
  - Announcements of exhibitions, xeroxes, price lists, reviews, letters, etc..., Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Announcements of exhibitions, xeroxes, price lists, reviews, letters, etc..., Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Announcements of exhibitions, xeroxes, price lists, reviews, letters, etc..., Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Announcements of exhibitions, xeroxes, price lists, reviews, letters, etc..., Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Announcements of exhibitions, xeroxes, price lists, reviews, letters, etc..., Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Letters, lists, Archives of American Art info, artist's statement, etc..., Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Multiple lists, chronology, etc..., Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Reviews and letters, exhibition info, etc..., Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Various exhibition info, 1996-1998 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Various exhibition info, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Publications other than reviews, Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Group shows in Europe, 1997-2002 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Group shows in the U.S.A., 1996-2002 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Xerox editions - "The Dream" and "Pomfleur", 1998, 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Oversize Series II: Original Artwork
  - Blonde in Blue, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Lew Ayres in "All Quiet on the Western Front", 2000 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Dornier - 17, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Maruru, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Sweetly Smiling, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Bill Anthony's Greatest Hits, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Flaming Creature, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Suburban Ambush, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Teckningan - exhibit poster, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Accretion 2009 - Series I: Record of Artwork
  - Artwork (copies), 2005 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Artwork (copies), 2006 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Artwork (copies), 2007 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Artwork (copies), 2008 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Artwork (copies), 2009 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Accretion 2009 - Series IV: Miscellany
  - Correspondence, exhibition info, records of damaged, altered or discovered artworks, 1955-2006 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Accretion 2013 - Series I: Record of artwork
  - Artwork (copies), 2009 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Artwork (copies), 2010 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Artwork (copies), 2011 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Artwork (copies), 2012 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Artwork (copies), 2013 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Mail Art sent to Sam Jedig (copies), 2009-2013 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Accretion 2013 - Series II: Original Artwork
  - Drawings for A New Approach to Figure Drawing, 2010 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Accretion 2013 - Series IV: Miscellany
  - Photographs, announcements, letters, commercial cartoons, a price list, decorative stamps, copy of envelope "Tribute to Judy Hoffberg", front door decor, 1965-2013 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Lists of discarded artworks, 2005-2013 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Clippings, 2007-2013 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Accretion 2022, 2021-2022; .1 linear feet in 1 folder in shared housing
  - Drawings (Mostly Print-Outs and Photocopies), 2021-2022 (Box Shared Fales 041, Folder 17)